Guide to the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated RL.00413
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Addresses Series, 1661-1991 and undated, 5 boxes
  - Anonymous Works, 1661-1777 and undated (Box WA 4)
    - Bristol newspaper and letter transcriptions, 1743-1777 and undated
      - Bristol letters to the editor, 1775 Oct. 7-1777 Jan. 22, 78 pages (Box WA 4)
        Handwritten transcriptions of letters to the editor of a publication identified only as "B.I.," presumably the Bristol Intelligencer. The letters debate the legality and justness of the American Revolution, including much discussion of the Americans' grievance "no taxation without representation" and whether this is a legally justifiable complaint in light of the Magna Carta, the colonies' charters, the policy of England in its other colonies, etc. The first letter in the exchange, a rebuttal of JW's "A Calm Address to the American Colonies," is by a writer very much in favor of the American Revolution and very hostile to Wesley. In the course of the debate Wesley himself writes twice to answer his critics, once on 1775 Nov. 25 and again on 1775 Dec. 2. The debate on America continues in subsequent letters by other writers, though with fewer references to Wesley's positions. 78 pages.
    - A brief Account of the Occassion, Process, and Issue of a Late Tryal at the Assize held at Gloucester, the Third of March 1743...Extract from Mr. Whitefield's letter, by John Wesley M.A., Fellow of Lincoln College, Oxford, 1743 and undated, 26 pages (Box WA 4)
      19th century transcription of a printed pamphlet written by John Wesley and published in 1748. Although found separately from the two items above, an unsigned note from FB indicates that he thought these pages may have been the product of the same, unidentified 19th century transcriber. The poem "A Prayer for King George" begins on p. 24, breaks off, and then begins again on the following pages.
    - A Short Account of the Progress of Wesleyan Methodism with Some Account of Other Sects of Alstonmoor during the Last Threescore Years--handwritten account, fourteen pages, 1845 Jan. (Box WA 4)
    - Untitled notes on fly sheets controversy, 1845-1847 (Box WA 4)
    - Watchnights--A Watchnight Sermon, manuscript, circa 1858 (Box WA 4)
    - A Brief Memoir of Ellen Standering...a scholar in the Heap Bridge Sabbath School, near Heywood, Lancashire, who died as a young girl, 1862, 8 pp. (Box WA 4)
      FB's description: A demonstration of the the deep piety and emphasis upon 'dying well' which carried over in some ways from Wesley's Methodism to Victorian Methodism." In copperplate script, bound.
    - Lecture on C. H. Spurgeon, undated (Box WA 4)
      Untitled and unsigned lecture, or series of lectures, on 19th-century Baptist preacher Charles Haddon Spurgeon. Possibly in the hand of F. F. Bretherton, which would date manuscript to early 20th century.
    - Sermon notes on Numbers 10:29, undated (Box WA 4)
    - Verses, copied from various sources, undated [mid-1800s] (Box WA 4)
      About eighteen poems, songs, or prayers, including: "The Man of Fashion, by the Revd. Charles Wesley"; "Lines to the Memory of the Revd. John Wesley, by E. Solomon"; "An account of the last illness and happy death of John Pawson, extracted from a letter by his Mother to his Grandmother"; "Reminiscence," by Jas. Montgomery, Esq.; and sonnets, acrostics, and other short poems.
- Volumes Series, 1620-1991 and undated, 30 boxes, 107 volumes
  Arranged in the following subseries: Letterbooks; Local Histories; Albums and Scrapbooks; and Writings and Addresses. The volumes are chiefly manuscripts, and take the form of letterbooks, diaries and journals, scrapbooks, notebooks, record books, and albums. The contents can include autographs; correspondence; memoirs; essays; photographs; engravings; ephemera such as Christams cards, tickets, and stamps; maps; clippings; notes; sermons; histories; and church records. The latter category includes Methodist church account and roll books, circuit schedules, year-by-year histories and journals of various chapels, meeting minutes, and Sunday School rolls. Subseries are arranged alphabetically. Some items are in short-hand. A sample of Wesley's own short-hand from one of his journal entries (1740) is included in an information folder in box WF1, along with illustrations of Society Tickets.
  - Letterbooks Subseries, circa 1753-1950 and undated, 8 boxes, 11 volumes
    Letterbooks containing approximately 2000 letters, dated from circa 1760-1950. Most items fall in the 19th century.
    - Letterbook 1: Wesleyan Presidents I (WP I), 1760-1968 and undated, circa 300 items (Box VOLS 1)
      Contains approximately 150 letters and a like number of engravings and ephemera, this volume contains some of the oldest correspondence of any letter-book in the collection. Highlights include original letters from Sarah Wesley and her brothers Charles and Samuel, Mary Bosanquet Fletcher, Joseph Benson, Adam Clarke, Thomas Coke, Alexander Mather, and many other important figures in the early history of Methodism. A fairly full transcript exists, done by FB in the late 1940s (prior to his later purchase of the album). [Note: This and the following album are also referred to as the Cole/Kirkby albums in some of FB's notes.]
    - Letterbook 2: Wesleyan Presidents II (WP II), 1781-1903 and undated, circa 65 letters (Box VOLS 2)
      Very similar to Letterbook WP I above, though smaller and in poorer condition. Contains letters from many Presidents of the Wesleyan Conference from the first half of the 19th century. No transcript exists.
    - Letterbook 3: Simpson A, 1808-1886 and undated, 149 letters (Box VOLS 3)
      The first of five scrapbooks compiled by David Simpson (1745-1799) and, more accurately, his descendants, especially Samuel Simpson. The latter is also the primary recipient of many of the later and shorter letters, especially in Volumes A and B. All five letterbooks contain approximately 1050 letters dating from 1799-1886. A and B are dated somewhat later than the other albums. A full index of this volume, completed by John Vickers in 1987, is available in Research Services.
    - Letterbook 4: Simpson B, 1838-1860 and undated, 134 letters (Box VOLS 3)
      Very similar to Simpson A, described above. A full index of this volume, completed by John Vickers in 1987, is available in Research Services.
    - Letterbook 5: Simpson C, 1799-1886 and undated, 145 letters (Box VOLS 4)
      Discovered in 2010, Letterbook Simpson C contains letters that are considerably older than those in A and B, and from more prominent figures in Methodist history. Included here are letters from such early figures as Adam Clarke, Isaac Clayton, Alexander Mather, and Theophilus Lessey.
    - Letterbook 6: Simpson D, 1804-1865 and undated, circa 390 letters (Box VOLS 5)
      Letterbook Simpson D is both the largest and, at present, least-indexed of the Simpson volumes. Some of the longer (and physically frailer) letters have been examined, however, and include a number of long letters from missionaries in India (D:388, Alfred Levell, India, to Eliza (sister), 1859 Nov. 7), New Zealand (D:391, W. Lowry, Auckland, to ??, 1844 Dec. 19). Also to be found here is long letter from 1803 in which the writer, John Dean, describes the current fears of a French invasion (D:153).
    - Letterbook 7: Simpson E, 1800-1869 and undated, circa 345 letters (Box VOLS 6)
      Similar to Simpson D, above, in chronological coverage and physical extent. Among the longer letters here E:202, Joseph Simpson to Theophilus Pugh, 1861 July 8, in which Simpson describes an interview he had many years earlier with Elizabeth Mortimer, shortly before her death (see Correspondence Series, Elizabeth (Ritchie) Mortimer Letters). Also to be found here is a long and early letter from a missionary in Honduras (E:292).
    - Letterbook 8: Anonymous, Literary and evangelical autographs, 1823-1871 and undated (Box VOLS 7)
      Inside cover contains penciled note "some good literary and evangelical autographs," possibly in FB's hand. Contains approximate 45 full length letters, only a few of which have been identified, including autograph letters (not yet authenticated) by the writers Sir Walter Scott, Thomas Hood, Hannah More, and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. The evangelical letters have not been identified. Album also contains several dozen engravings and numerous shorter autograph notes. 100 pages, of which some 30-40 are blank.
    - Letter book 9: Anonymous, Hull conference letter-book and album, 1838-1851 and undated (Box VOLS 7)
      Untitled volume--title assigned by archivist. Not about Hull, but perhaps written and compiled at various meetings in Hull over the course of 15 to 20 years, as most entries mention Hull addresses as the location of the writer. Autograph entries in many hands by Wesleyan ministers and, in particular, a high proportion of missionaries. The latter often refer to their postings in some way: Henry Bleby's 1851 entry details the history of Coke Chapel, founded in Kingston, Jamaica, in 1792; Benjamin Clough, missionary to Ceylon, records the Lord's Prayer in Singhalese; and other entries include one entitled "Pity Poor Africa!" and a Bible verse written in Chippewha. Entries are inscribed on the pages, but also glued and tipped in; portrait engravings of the writers are laid in. Circa 100 pages; not examined closely due to volume's fragility.
    - Letter book 10: Steele, John, Letters and various other Documents copied from Originals and other Authentic Sources by Mr. John Steele, late of Barnard Castle now of Penketh nr Warrington and recopied by James Little, Warrington 1867, 1753-1825, 1849-1867, and undated, 64 items
      Documentation FB provided with this gift in the 1970s stated that these mid-19th century copies are the earliest-known sources for many of these letters. Since this has not been verified against more recent scholarship and the album contains some thirty letters of John Wesley, a full index is provided below; index compiled by John Vickers in 1987, in order by page number.
      - 3-4. Taylor, Joseph, Notice of the Reverend Joseph Taylor, undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 4. Rowell, Jacob, Original mode of Expulsion or sending out of the Methodist Society taken from the ms. book of the venerable Jacob Rowell and presumed to have been used by him, undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 5-9. Bradburn, Samuel, General rules to be observed in preparing for the pulpit by the Reverend, undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 11. Wesley, John, near London, to Duncan McAllum, n.p., 1782 Oct. 24 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 10-16. Wesley, John, London, Edinburgh, and Bristol, to Samuel Bradburn, n.p., 1778 Oct. 17; 1779 Feb. 13, Oct. 10, and June 19; 1780 Sept. 16, Oct. 28; 1781 June 16, 7 letters (Box VOLS 7)
      - 17. Wesley, John, n.p., to Hester Ann Rogers, then Miss Roe, n.p., 1782 Apr. 13 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 18. Wesley, John, Leeds, to Robert Wilkinson, one of his preachers, n.p., 1769 Aug. 5 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 18. Wesley, John, Bristol, to Joseph Thompson, n.p., 1770 Sept. 3 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 19. Wesley, John, Near London, to John Mason, n.p., 1790 Jan. 13 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 20. Taylor, Joseph, Burslem, to James Rogers, n.p., 1803 Feb. 23 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 21. Taylor, Joseph, n.p., to Matthew Lumb, n.p., undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 22-23. Palmer, William, Burslem, to James Rogers, n.p., 1803 Feb. 23 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 24. Myles, William, North Shields, to James Rogers, n.p., 1805 Nov. 5 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 26-27. Fletcher, Mrs. [Mary], Madeley, to Miss Tripp, n.p., 1812 June 20 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 27. Wesley, John, London, to presumed to Charles Atmore, Colne, Lancaster, 1788 Dec. 6 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 28-30. Wesley, John, Cork, Epworth, London, and Bristol, to Jasper Winscom, n.p., 1785 May 9, 1786 June 17; 1788 July 16; 1790 Mar. 13, 4 letters (Box VOLS 7)
      - 30-32. Wesley, John, London, Birmingham, Manchester, and Bristol, to Robert Costerdine, n.p., 1775 Oct. 20; 1776 Mar. 26, Apr. 7, and Dec. 27; 1785 Sept. 4, 5 letters (Box VOLS 7)
      - 32. Moore, Henry, n.p., to Robert Costerdine, n.p., 1785 July 7 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 32. Mason, John, n.p., to Robert Costerdine, n.p., 1779 Mar. 31 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 33. Tatton, Thomas, Biddulph, to Robert Costerdine, n.p., 1772 July 6 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 34. Wesley, John, n.p., to Mrs. Crosby, London, 1757 July 1 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 34. Wesley, John, Sunderland, to Henry Brook, Dublin, 1768 May 25 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 35-36. Wesley, John, Whitby, to Mrs. Freeman, Dublin, 1788 June 12 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 35-36. Wesley, John, Castlebar, to Mrs. Freeman, Dublin, 1789 May 20 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 35-36. Wesley, John, n.p., to Mrs. Freeman, Dublin, 1788 May (Box VOLS 7)
      - 36. Wesley, John, n.p., to John Bredin, n.p., 1773 Sept. 18 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 37. Wesley, John, Bradford, to Adam Clarke, n.p., 1777 Sept. 19 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 37. Wesley, John, n.p., to James Barry, n.p., 1776 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 38. Wesley, John, Plymouth Dock, to William Thom, n.p., 1789 Aug. 30 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 38-39. Wesley, John, Bristol, to Hester Ann Rogers, n.p., 1783 Mar. 18 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 39-51. Roe, Hester Ann & Mrs. Rogers, n.p., to ?, n.p., 1782 Mar.-Apr. (Box VOLS 7)
      - 52. Ritchie, Elizabeth, n.p., to Mrs. Bradburn, n.p., undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 53. Bradburn, Samuel, Bolton, to Rev. J. Holland [Unitarian minister of Bolton], Bolton [?], 1805 Mar. 24 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 54-56. Bradford, Joseph, Sheffield, to James Rogers, n.p., 1805 Aug. 2 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 56-57. Pawson, John, Wakefield, to James Rogers, n.p., 1805 Aug. 26 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 58-61. Moore, Henry, Leeds, to James Rogers, n.p., 1806 Feb. 4 and July 8, 2 letters (Box VOLS 7)
      - 61-63. McDonald, James, Dewsbury, to Miss Sophia Bradburn, n.p., 1821 Sept. 28 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 63-64. Shackleton, William, Tanfield, to J. Mann, n.p., 1858 May 10 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 65. Dove, Christopher, Leeds, to James Everett, n.p., 1849 Sept. 24 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 66. Gaulter, Henry, n.p., to Miss Sophia Bradburn, n.p., undated [postmarked 1820 May 10] (Box VOLS 7)
      - 67-71. Nelson, George, Bolton, to Mr. Armitage, Stockport, 1851 Feb. 27 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 72-73. ?, n.p., to ?, n.p., 1753 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 73. Bradburn, Samuel, n.p., to ?, n.p., undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 74. Several authors, Barnard Castle, to ?, n.p., 1768 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 75-76. Rowell, Jacob, n.p., to ?, n.p., undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 76-77. ?, Sketch of a sermon taken from Rev. J. Rowell's Memorandum book, undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 78-85. Pearce, G. L., n.p., to Rev. John Little, n.p., 1858 July 7 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 86-87. Fletcher, Mrs., Note on her husband, 24 years after his death, undated (Box VOLS 7)
      - 86-87. Fletcher, Mrs., Madeley, Draft of a letter to an unnamed correspondent, 1809 Sept. 18 (Box VOLS 7)
      - 189. ?, n.p., Note regarding Samuel Bradburn as President, and the verses he wrote in reply to Joseph Benson's message 'Cobbler, go not beyond thy last'. [Ne suter ultra], 1799 (Box VOLS 7)
      - At end.. ?, Printed copy of The Methodist Pocket Book for 1825, pp. 1-12: Memoir of Mrs. Hannah More, 1825 (Box VOLS 7)
    - Osborn, George, Collection of letters and broadsheets, &c., on Wesleyan Reform Movement, circa 1812-1893 (Box VOLS 8)
      Letterbook and scrapbook compiled by historian and Wesleyan President George Osborn. Many letters on Wesleyan Reform Movement; also Methodist Recorder series of Book Room Letters by the Wesleys, eminent Methodist women, etc. Circa 150 pages; volume not examined closely yet due to its fragile condition.
  - Local Histories Subseries, 1768-1938, 1965, and undated, 4 boxes, 23 volumes
    Church account and roll books, circuit schedules, year-by-year histories and journals of various chapels, meeting minutes, Sunday School rolls, and a variety of other records of churches and circuits in Barnsley, Burnley, Hull, Leeds, Lincolnshire, Sunderland, and other areas of England. Wesleyan Methodist and Primitive Methodist churches are both represented in the collection. Arranged alphabetically by community, circuit name, or county.
    [Attention: Handle with care. May need conservation prior to access. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.]
    - Barnsley Circuit, 1803-1920
      - Methodist Sunday School, Barnsley, account book, 1803-1888 (Box VOLS 9)
        "Established 27th Nov. 1803." Account book covering 85 years of expenditures for the Sunday School. Circa 100 pages.
      - Barnsley Circuit account book, 1811-1840 (Box VOLS 9)
        Volume containing financial records primarily, but also including minutes and resolutions pertaining to quarterly meetings of the Barnsley Circuit. Circa 250 pp.
      - Barnsley Circuit Roll Book, 1832-1843 (Box VOLS 9)
        Lists members of classes by place. The letters LP (local minister) and AL (Assistant leader) appear by appropriate class members' names. Printed instructions on each page specify to record "dead...removed, fallen, left, or ?, as the case may be" beside names as needed. 190 pp.
      - Barnsley Circuit schedule book, 1841-1848 (Box VOLS 9)
        Volume listing information about the Barnsley Circuit of the P.M. (Primitive Methodist) Connexion. Lists names of the various places where classes met in the circuit and names of members in each class. 190 pp.
      - Barnsley Circuit Missionary Account Book, 1888-1920 (Box VOLS 9)
        Notes on income and expenditures with notes on missionary fund, especially the African Fund. Circa 160 pp.
    - Bexhill, "Diary of the Sackville Road Chapel Scheme, 1895-1896 (Box VOLS 9)
      Account book and journal of the construction Wesleyan Chapel at Bexhill, including several news clippings about it and subscription lists of donors. Circa 30 pages.
    - Burnley, Chapel account books and journals, 1839-1868, 2 volumes (Box VOLS 9)
      Includes correspondence, letter fragments, and other material related to Wesley Chapel, Burnley.
    - Journal--notes concerning the building of the Wesley Chapel, including portraits of caretakers, 1839-1840s (Box VOLS 9)
    - Chapel schedule, various circuits, 1820s-1850s (Box VOLS 10)
      Volume containing printed questionnaires that have the answers written in by hand about different chapels in various Methodist Church circuits in Great Britain. Includes information about each chapel's administrative, physical, and financial conditions as well as their Sabbath schools. Circa 300-400 pages--not examined closely due to item's fragility.
      [Attention: CLOSED to patron access until preservation completed (spine and cover deteriorating; interior pages in fair to good condition). Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.
    - Hull Circuit, 1826-1868
      - Hull, Quarterly Meeting, 1826-1833 (Box VOLS 10)
        Minutes kept on resolutions made by the Hull Circuit. Circa 200 pages--not examined closely due to item's fragility.
        [Attention: CLOSED to patron access until preservation completed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.]
      - P. M. [Primitive Methodist] Chapels in Hull Districts, 1866-1868 (Box VOLS 10)
        From cover: "Copy of financial details (and accomodation) from Chapel Schedules." Content extends to 1867, not 1868 as noted on cover. Circa 50 pages of records for various circuits in Hull. Starting from back cover, volume is labeled "A list of deceased Trustees"--this contains only one partial page of names on the inside. Remainder of volume is blank.
      - Circuit Plans, Hull--all printed material bound, 1821-1841 (Box VOLS 11)
    - Kirkoswald Circuit: "Notes and Comments on the Kirkoswald Circuit (Cumberland) by W.E. Lancaster--with a few items laid in, undated (Box VOLS 10)
    - Leeds, 1768-1777, 1855, 1906, and undated (Box VOLS 12)
      Circuit accounts and miscellaneous volumes from Leeds and nearby communities.
      - Leeds Circuit Accounts, 1768-1777 and 1906 (transcribed), 2 volumes, 81 leaves (Box VOLS 12)
        First and second Circuit Steward's Book for the Leeds Circuit, monies received and disbursed. Anonymous transcription, 1906, does not identify source of original. Among many other names, JW and John Pawson mentioned several times as being reimbursed.
        [Attention: May need conservation prior to use. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.]
      - Goldsworth, William, "Arithmetic by Wm. Goldsworth," Dec. 31 1855 (Box VOLS 12)
        Arithmetic book and possible account book of William Goldsworth, identified as living in Wortley, Near Leeds. Much of the book lists items purchased and monies received, though it is unclear whether these were Goldsworth's personal expenses or the accounts for a Methodist church or circuit.
    - Lincolnshire Manuscripts and Research (Box VOLS 12)
      A variety of original manuscript volumes, transcribed volumes, clippings, correspondence, and research. Most of the work appears to have been compiled and transcribed by Marmaduke Riggall circa 1900-1925, then passed along to FB by way of the Wesley Historical Society or F. F. Bretherton. Also includes an inventory, perhaps compiled by Riggall and updated by FB in the 1960s, though not all items on the list have been foundArranged in two boxes as Volumes and Folders.
      RELATED MATERIAL: Volumes only are housed in this box. For loose materials, see Subjects Files, Lincolnshire.
      - Methodists of East Lincolnshire, Vol. 1, 1769-1788, and Vol. 2, 1789-1824, as recorded in the Grimsby and Horncastle Circuits; transcribed by M. Riggall, 1922, 2 volumes (Box VOLS 12)
      - Methodist Standard's Quarter Book (Horncastle Circuit), 1792-1798; transcribed by M. Riggall, 1909, 1 volume (Box VOLS 12)
      - Hundred of Yarborough's Association, 1820-1834, 1 volume (Box VOLS 12)
        Rules and Regulations of the Association of Yarborough; notes on court cases, 1820-1834; and a list of rules and regulations for persons convicted of felonies and misdemeanors.
      - Ulcebe Class Book--record of tickets, donations and circuit attendance, 1829-1835, 1 volume (Box VOLS 12)
      - Norton, John H., [Membership Roll], 1847-1850, 1 volume (Box VOLS 12)
        Inside cover refers to Norton as serving a congregation at Louthe from 1847-1850; contributions have been added in pencil, apparently at the distribution of tickets.
    - Manchester: "Great Bridgewater Street Chapel, 1801-1898", 25 leaves (Box VOLS 12)
      Hardbound volume with clippings glued in, detailing the history of the chapel. Clippings appear to be from the Manchester Weekly Times, 1898.
      RELATED MATERIAL: other materials on church history in Manchester can be found in the Subject Files, Manchester.
    - Sunderland: B. A. Hurd Barley, "Records of Methodism in Sunderland," 1801-1896, approximately 200 pages (Box VOLS 12)
      A year-by-year chronology of Methodism in 19th century Sunderland. Two pages are allotted to each year, with notes in recurrent categories such as Ministers, Candidates for Ministry, Circuit Finance, and many others. Many entries include quotes from various Methodist authors, which comment in some way on events of the year; printed items tipped in to numerous pages.
      RELATED MATERIAL: Loose materials, almost entirely from the final endpapers, were removed to the Subjects Series, Sunderland history.
  - Albums and Scrapbooks Subseries, 1620, 1781-1937, 1991 and undated, 8 boxes, 21 volumes